Guide to the Voices of Brooklyn oral histories 2008.031
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Voices of Brooklyn oral histories: Sports and leisure, 2008-; 2008.031.6
  - King, Albert, 2009 November 4; 2008.031.6.002
    Beginning his interview, Albert King recalls his journey from childhood to his teens in school and on the basketball courts of Brooklyn. He talks about his older brother Bernard King as a street ball player and later as a New York Knick. He fondly remembers his own youth; playing ball, emulating star players of the '70s, building a reputation, and training under the legendary coach Gil Reynolds. He discusses his time in his high school team within the surroundings of the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn and meeting the demands of his parents at home in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. He speaks about experiencing blatant or subtle racism during his time as a kid. King shares some details on his parents and how basketball flourished in the family. He describes his time as a college player at the University of Maryland, who his teammates were, and how they coalesced into a good team. King reminisces more about being a kid in Fort Greene. He describes the rush of playing as a professional and his ability to transition to running a business. Interview conducted via telephone by Sady Sullivan.
    African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Social life and customs; Basketball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Basketball players |z United States; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene Park (New York, N.Y.); Games |x Street |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Maryland; New Jersey; School sports |z New York (State) |z New York; Sports for children |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Kramer, Allan, 2008 September 4; 2008.031.6.003
    Allan F. Kramer II was born, raised, and resides in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn. He attended St. Savior School and Brooklyn Preparatory School. He graduated from the College of the Holy Cross in 1972 and from Pratt Institute in 1979, attaining a graduate degree in Information Science. He worked in publishing and took an interest in many Brooklyn organizations; including as a volunteer and committee member at the Brooklyn Botanic Garden since 1978; Board of Directors of CAMBA; Past Board member and President of the private Montauk Club in Park Slope; a member of the Municipal Club of the City; Board member of the Prospect Park YMCA (Young Men's Christian Association); Executive Board Member and the Treasurer of Reel Works: Teen Filmmaking; Board member and President of the New York Memory Center; and a Life Member of the Society of Old Brooklynites.
    In this interview, while onsite at the Montauk Club during an event, Allan F. Kramer II begins by talking about his family's long residence in Brooklyn. He recalls his early years of living in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn and visits to Prospect Park. Kramer recounts where he attended school. He speaks about the Montauk Club via his family's membership. Kramer's adulthood didn't initially include much time at the club because of his career, he says, but he made up for it by later becoming a Board member and President. He describes the changing nature of the club; historically and structurally. Kramer shares some history of the neighborhood, as well. In closing, he gives a short tour and points out visually impressive features. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Buildings, structures, etc.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Historic buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic preservation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Private clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Societies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Voluntarism |z New York (State) z Kings County |x Societies, etc.; Brooklyn Botanic Garden
  - Nisselson, Alan, 2009 March 26; 2008.031.6.004
    Alan Nisselson was born in 1947 and raised in the Coney Island neighborhood of Brooklyn. While the family was living above a delicatessen in Coney Island, they opened a custard stand near Steeplechase Park and put Nisselson to work when he was a young boy. Later in his youth, the family moved north to a Kings Highway address. Work at the custard stand ended in 1965 and young Nisselson went on to work for the City Parks Department in Brooklyn for a few summers. He attained an undergraduate degree from American University in 1968 and a doctoral degree from Brooklyn Law in 1976. With a master's degree in business administration from New York University as well, he became an Assistant United States Attorney in the Southern District of New York. He also worked with creditors' rights firms. As of 2017, Nisselson resided in the Carroll Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn, was a partner at Windels Marx Lane & Mittendorf, and served as a trustee in U.S. Bankruptcy Courts and elaborate Chapter 11 cases. He is on the Board of Trustees at Brooklyn Historical Society.
    In this interview, Alan Nisselson speaks in detail about the origins of his family's seaside custard stand business in the Coney Island neighborhood of Brooklyn. He recalls the stand's offerings, the layout, and the operation. Nisselson also remembers the surroundings of his home, school, and work life within Coney Island. He recollects his swimming routine at Steeplechase Park and enjoying and mastering many of the attractions at that amusement park. He adds details about the sideshow performers, the family that lived on the Thunderbolt roller coaster property, the parachute jump, and custard stand competitors. He then shares some of what his parents told him about older venues; such as Luna Park, Feltman's and the bathhouses. Some less pleasant memories for Nisselson were the demands of summer work when friends were vacationing, segregation of private swimming pools, his mother's workplace accident, and the prevalence of rats. In closing, he reflects on his unique childhood and observes the changes to Surf Avenue and the seaside in 2009. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Amusement parks |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Buildings, structures, etc.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Child labor |z New York (State) |z New York; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Desserts; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Outdoor recreation; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Shuba, George, 2008 July 23; 2008.031.6.005
    George Thomas "Shotgun" Shuba was born in Youngstown, Ohio in 1924. He played in Little League ball clubs and high school baseball as a boy. After a try-out to be a professional baseball player in 1943, the Dodgers club signed him in 1944. In 1946, he was playing as a left fielder for the Dodgers' farm team, the Montreal Royals, when he met teammate Jackie Robinson. His on-deck greeting upon Robinson's crossing home plate at a Jersey City season opener was a publicly notable effort at racial tolerance. Shuba spent time in an Alabama minor-league team for the Dodgers before he was ordered up to Brooklyn's Ebbets Field in 1948. Called upon infrequently by the Brooklyn Dodgers in 1949 and 1950, the left-handed pinch hitter stepped up his appearances in 1951 and subsequently in three World Series, including their winning season in 1955. He was a frequent resident of the Bossert Hotel in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood for much of his career. After playing for Montreal again in 1956, he went on to become a postal clerk in Youngstown. Married since age thirty-three, Shuba was a father of three. As of his death in 2014, he had eight grandchildren.
    Beginning his interview, George Thomas "Shotgun" Shuba mentions a few factors that led to his time in Brooklyn as one of the Dodgers. He then recalls details and stories about teammates, plays at Ebbets Field, team President Walter O'Malley, living in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood, and messages from local fans. He contrasts Brooklyn baseball with other major league New York teams of the late-1940s to mid-1950s. He turns back to some personal details; including the source of his nickname, his ambidextrous ability on the field, and his overactive thyroid. He compares the business of baseball of then with the twenty-first century. In the middle of the interview, Shuba recalls Jackie Robinson in terms of character and in plays. He returns to his own background; his post-Dodgers years and family life, as well as the lives of his parents, and his earliest times playing ball. He closes with memories of a 1985 Dodgers reunion and a salute to the Brooklyn fans. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Baseball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baseball fans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baseball fields |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baseball players |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Florida; New York (N.Y.); Brooklyn Dodgers (Baseball team); O'Malley, Walter, 1903-1979
  - Sobers, Mary DeSaussure, 2009 January 21; 2008.031.6.006
    Mary DeSaussure Sobers, a track runner from the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant, became the first African American female to run in a sanctioned track meet when she participated in the Olympic Carnival, sponsored by the New York City Department of Parks, in 1945. Sobers won gold medal for the forty-yard dash. She and her twin sister Martha were born in Utahville, South Carolina in 1931. They attended Girls' High School in Bedford-Stuyvesant and helped form the Trailblazers, the first girls track team under the auspices of the Police Athletic League (PAL) in Brooklyn. Both DeSaussure sisters went to the Olympic tryouts in 1948. Sobers went on to become a coach and adviser to the Queens Trailblazers Track Club. She worked as a secretary at a shoe-polish plant as well as a manufacturer of vacuum-cleaners, but her long term workplace was Elmhurst Hospital Center in Queens. She retired in 1997. She married Lowell Sobers in 1958. The couple resided in the Springfield Gardens neighborhood of Queens when the interview took place in 2009.
    In her lengthy interview, Mary DeSaussure Sobers recalls her life by way of many of her memories, press clippings, photographs and the people she's known. She tells about recently receiving an honorary award, and then shares biographical details about herself, twin sister Martha, and their parents. She connects the politics of the 2008 presidential elections to disrespectful children of the era. Sobers begins to tell the tale of her first track meet experience late in the interview's first hour, and comes back to that and an all-borough meet in hours two and three, with many offshoot topics along the way. The initial track meet experience was a personal success, but was blunted by racism in the awarding of medals. She also discusses sexism in sports as well as in her personal upbringing. She looks back at the historic arc of civil rights. Sobers shares details on people dear to her, like her sister Martha, and friend Inge Auerbacher. Sobers also speaks of her genealogy research on her family. Throughout, she is mindful of instilling children with a positive outlook and goals, using her experience as lessons for them. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    African Americans |x Civil rights |x History |y 20th century; African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Social life and customs; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Discrimination in sports |z United States; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Genealogy; Girls |x Education (Secondary) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School sports |z New York (State) |z New York; Sports -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sports for children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women runners |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Voices of Brooklyn oral histories: Veterans and wartime, 1998-; 2008.031.7
  This series includes oral histories collected through several projects undertaken by Brooklyn Historical Society beginning in 1998. The assembled series took shape in 2008 under the project title "Brooklyn History Makers." The ongoing oral history series, retitled in 2016, features a range of narrators: Service members from the United Services Organization, Army Reserves, Women's Army Corps, and those who fought in World War II and Vietnam, recall personal moments and the changes they have observed in their Brooklyn neighborhoods over decades.
  - Bourdonnay, Katherine, 2007 March 2; 2008.031.7.001
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bourdonnay, Katherine
  - Fletcher, Ozzie, 2008 March 25; 2008.031.7.002
  - Garcia, Marc, 2011 February 18; 2008.031.7.003
    Colonel Marc Garcia, of the United States Army Reserve and the United States Department of State, was born in 1962 in Brooklyn, New York to parents of Colombian and Haitian heritage. Garcia grew up in Queens, where he graduated from Holy Cross High School. Garcia attended the historically-African American Hampton Institute (now Hampton University) in Virginia, where he joined the Reserve Officers' Training Corps (ROTC) and the Virginia Army National Guard. As a freshman in college, Garcia was promoted meritoriously to the position of sergeant, and as a sophomore in college was commissioned as a second lieutenant. Upon graduation from college, Garcia moved to Brooklyn, where he worked for Assemblyman Roger L. Green as a legislative aide, and became an elected county commissioner. Garcia spent time working at the United Nations before leaving to work in the United States Department of State as a foreign service specialist under Ambassador Vernon Walters, a retired three-star general. In 2009, Garcia was activated as a member of the Virginia Army National Guard and was sent to Iraq to serve as a Military Police Battalion Commander. When he returned in November of 2010, Garcia was promoted to Colonel for his performance in Iraq. At the time of the 2011 interview, Garcia looked forward to an official promotion to Colonel.
    In this interview, Colonel Marc Garcia provides a detailed account of his military and civilian career, which was spent as a member of the Virginia National Guard and a foreign services specialist at the United States Department of State. In the interview's beginning, Garcia describes the evolution of Brooklyn throughout the 1980s, including from being filled with renters and artists, to being filled with single-family homes. He discusses workaday life at the offices of New York Assemblyman Roger L. Green and the economic development of Brooklyn that resulted from the Metrotech Plan. At the interview's end, Garcia discusses his service in the Iraq War, which led to his decoration as a Colonel in the division of Military Police. He describes the next day's pinning ceremony and celebration plans thereafter. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Civil Service |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (State) |x Politics and government; Soldiers |x Family relationships |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Veterans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; War on Terrorism, 2001-2009
  - Gruber, Ruth, 2008 February 7; 2008.031.7.004
    Ruth Gruber was an award-winning Jewish American journalist, photographer, and humanitarian. Born to immigrants in Brooklyn in 1911, she became the youngest person in the world to receive a PhD, at age twenty--with a dissertation on Virginia Woolf. In 1935, she became the first correspondent to travel to the Siberian Gulag and Soviet Arctic. She went on to author nineteen books and wrote several memoirs documenting her experiences. Photography was a component of her earliest reportage; her groundbreaking work as a photojournalist spanned more than five decades on four continents. Gruber was appointed by Secretary of the Interior Harold Ickes in 1941 to report on conditions in the Alaska Territory. In 1947, Gruber's photographs documenting the harrowing voyage of the Exodus 1947 were sent internationally via wire services to thousands of newspapers and magazines, and transformed attitudes toward the plight of Jewish refugees and Holocaust survivors after the war. She lived in Manhattan, where the interview occurred in 2008. A mother to two, stepmother to three, a grandmother and great-grandmother to many, she died in 2016.
    Sources: Gruber, Ruth. Haven: The Dramatic Story of 1,000 World War II Refugees and How They Came to America (New York, NY: Open Road Media, 1983). "Ruth Gruber, Photojournalist." International Center of Photography, https://www.icp.org/exhibitions/ruth-gruber-photojournalist. Accessed 25 May 2017. Turner, Philip. "Virginia Woolf and Ruth Gruber, Driven to Create as Women." The Great Gray Bridge, www.philipsturner.com/2012/04/15/virginia-woolf-ruth-gruber-create-women/ Accessed 25 May 2017.
    In this interview, Ruth Gruber, PhD recalls life as a child and young adult in the Williamsburg and Bushwick neighborhoods of Brooklyn in the nineteen-teens and twenties. She goes into family history of parents and grandparents, and her young life at home. Gruber recalls teachers who made formative impressions on her. She shares the accomplishments of a brother in medicine, a son in public health, and a daughter's reporting and childrearing. Gruber reflects on her studies and getting to know Virginia Woolf. She remembers her pursuit of a career in journalism that took a turn with her connection to explorer Vilhjalmur Steffanson; who shared his knowledge of the Siberian Arctic so that she could pursue an interview there with Soviet scientist Otto Shmidt. She identifies two other major reporting moments; 1948's Arab-Israeli War and the refugee crisis of the Exodus 1947. Gruber picks out several memorable images of her Brooklyn youth; including the Williamsburg Bridge, the temple her father attended, and Bushwick Public Library. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Arab-Israeli conflict; Arctic regions |x Discovery and exploration |x American; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Israel; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Feminism |z New York (State) |z New York; German Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jews; Jews, American |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Journalists -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographers |z New York (State) |z New York; Russia; Teachers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Women authors, American; Exodus 1947 (Ship); Gruber, Harry, 1907-; Gruber, Ruth, 1911-2016; Huggins, Willis Nathaniel; Michaels, David, 1954-; Shmidt, Otto I︠U︡lʹevich, 1891-1956; Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1879-1962
  - Mussen, Kathy, 2007 February 26; 2008.031.7.006
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Mussen, Katherine
  - Palo, Lucy Anbrosino, 2008 December 15; 2008.031.7.007
    Lucy Anbrosino was born in 1919. Her childhood in the Coney Island neighborhood of Brooklyn was plagued by the loss of her father and the family's poverty. With her family unable to care for her, she was institutionalized during the Great Depression; within that time she was misdiagnosed as insane, although she likely suffered from a severe learning disability, and spent much of her teens doing chores on a farm in rural New York State. After release as an eighteen-year-old, Anbrosino returned to Coney Island and took on jobs including mangler work at a laundry, adding frills to dresses, and adding color to artificial flowers. Later factory work included the manufacture of sweaters and clothespins. In the last few years of World War II, Anbrosino joined her brothers in war-work; she was a spot-welder on battleship hulls in Port Newark, New Jersey, then measured bullets and anti-aircraft cannons at a Brooklyn factory, and also attached buttons to Navy pea coats at another factory in the city. Also in the 1940s, she met her husband while working at an apple coring facility in Manhattan. She took his name, Palo, and had children. Lucy Anbrosino Palo died in 2011.
    In the interview, Lucy Anbrosino Palo begins with the story of her parents meeting and describes the family's difficulties in her childhood. She talks about her institutionalization at a few facilities and overcoming a learning disability. Much of the discussion revolves around her hard work during the Second World War. With short detours into other topics along the way, Palo delivers many details about her spot-welding work on battleships, being treated for poisoning from galvanized steel, what workers drank and ate on breaks at the Port Newark shipyard, how she was paid, and her mother's collecting of the adult children's wages. Additionally, Palo describes other war-related work on anti-aircraft guns in a Brooklyn factory and remembers how society took on a different look during the war. Palo also delves into her personal history; such as her life during the Great Depression and living with a difficult husband who died at an early age. Palo's son, Michael (also an oral history narrator in this series), makes a few comments during the recording. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Air raid warning systems; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Children -- Institutional care; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Factories |z New York (State) |z New York; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Navy-yards and naval stations; New Jersey; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parenting; Shipbuilding -- New Jersey; Ships |x Welding; World War, 1939-1945 |x Women |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Elizabeth-PA Marine Terminal (N.J.); Palo, Lucy Anbrosino
  - Palo, Michael, 2008 November 18; 2008.031.7.008
    Michael Palo was born to Italian American immigrants in Brooklyn, New York in 1948. (His mother, Lucy Anbrosino Palo, was also interviewed and is in the same series.) Upon graduating high school, he was drafted into the Vietnam War where he was deployed for a year. He moved back to Brooklyn after the war, worked in clinical systems for hospitals, and has been married three times. He has two children with his second wife; a son and a daughter. When the interview took place in 2008, he was living in Staten Island and was heavily involved with veterans organizations.